<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Dart | Shailen Tuli's tech blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://shailen.github.com/blog/categories/dart/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shailen.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-25T12:22:49-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shailen.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shailen Tuli]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[using boolean expressions for assignment in Dart]]></title>
    <link href="http://shailen.github.com/blog/2012/11/17/using-boolean-expressions-for-assignment-in-dart/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-17T21:52:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shailen.github.com/blog/2012/11/17/using-boolean-expressions-for-assignment-in-dart</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I often use boolean evaluation in Javascript for assignment:</p>

<pre><code>var Point = function(options) {
  options = options || {};
  this.x = options['x'] || 0;
  this.y = options['y'] || 0;
}
</code></pre>

<p>And in Ruby, it is idiomatic to do something like this:</p>

<pre><code>age ||= 16; // if age is `nil` or `false`, assign it a value of 16
</code></pre>

<p>or, this:</p>

<pre><code>a, b, c = 1, 2, 3
d = a &amp;&amp; b &amp;&amp; c
// d gets the value of c, 3
</code></pre>

<p>In each case, the boolean expressions return the value of the last evaluation. Can I do something similar in Dart?
Is this code legal?</p>

<pre><code>var x; // x is null
var y = x || 10;
</code></pre>

<p>In checked mode, no; in unchecked mode, this works, but the result may surprise you.</p>

<p>Based on other languages I have used, I would expect <code>y</code> to equal <code>10</code>.
In Dart, this does not happen and <code>y</code> gets assigned a value of <code>false</code>. Why? Since <code>10</code> is not explicitly <code>true</code>, it evaluates to
<code>false</code>. All things that are not explicitly <code>true</code> in Dart, are false (see my <a href="http://shailen.github.com/blog/2012/11/16/booleans-in-dart/">post</a>
from yesterday if this isn't clear).</p>

<p>Now, in checked mode (you are using checked mode, right?), <code>y</code> doesn't get a value at all because we get an error:</p>

<pre><code>Unhandled exception:
type 'Null' is not a subtype of type 'bool' of 'boolean expression'.
</code></pre>

<p>This is Dart's way of telling us that it is not going to do implicit boolean conversion for us when using <code>||</code> and it expects to see a boolean where it
now sees a <code>null</code> (<code>x</code> is null).  Changing the code to:</p>

<pre><code>var y = 5 || 10;
</code></pre>

<p>we get a slightly different error message:</p>

<pre><code>Unhandled exception:
type 'int' is not a subtype of type 'bool' of 'boolean expression'.
</code></pre>

<p>No good. Dart wants booleans around the <code>||</code>. This works fine, but it isn't what we are looking for:</p>

<pre><code>int x = 10;
bool y = x % 3 == 1 || x % 5 == 2;
// y is true
</code></pre>

<p>So, is there a correct way to handle assignment based on boolean evaluation? Yes. Don't rely on <code>||</code> or <code>&amp;&amp;</code> to implicitly
handle this for you; instead, explicitly check for truthyness yourself:</p>

<pre><code>int y = x == null ? 0 : x;
</code></pre>

<p>If <code>x</code> is null, <code>y</code> will be <code>0</code>; else, it will have the value of <code>x</code>. Quite clear and readable.</p>

<p>Boolean based assignment is common in JavaScript because there we don't have as rich an understanding
of keyword arguments and default values as Dart has. In Dart, we can do this:</p>

<pre><code>myFunction({x: 0, y: 0}) {
  ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>If you need to check whether a parameter was passed a value or not, you can easily do so:</p>

<pre><code>myFunction([x=0]) {
  if (?x) {
    ...
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The lessons of all this? <strong>Use checked mode</strong>. Don't rely on Dart's boolean expressions to magically return boolean values; if such values
are needed, obtain them directly yourself. Be explicit. Use default arguemnts in functions and methods. Use <code>?</code> to check if a parameter was passed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[booleans in dart]]></title>
    <link href="http://shailen.github.com/blog/2012/11/16/booleans-in-dart/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-16T18:32:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shailen.github.com/blog/2012/11/16/booleans-in-dart</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We've all written code that looks something like this:</p>

<pre><code>if (x) {
  // do something
} else {
  // do something else
}
</code></pre>

<p>In Javascript, the <code>if (x)</code> would evaluate to false if <code>x</code> was <code>false</code>, <code>null</code>, <code>undefined</code>, the number <code>0</code> (or <code>0.0</code>),
an <code>''</code> or <code>NaN</code> (these are all falsey in Javascript); otherwise it would evaluate to true.</p>

<p>If this code were rewritten in Python, the <code>if (x)</code> would evaluate to false if <code>x</code> was <code>None</code>, <code>false</code>, zero (<code>0</code>,
<code>0.0</code>, <code>0L</code>, etc.), an empty string (<code>''</code>), list (<code>[]</code>), tuple (<code>()</code>) or dict(<code>{}</code>);
otherwise it would evaluate to true.</p>

<p>So, what are the truthy and falsey lists for Dart? To answer that, let's look at what the
language spec says about booleans:</p>

<pre><code>Boolean conversion maps any object o into a boolean. Boolean conversion is defined  by the function
  (bool v){
    assert(v != null);
    return identical(v, true);
  }(o)
</code></pre>

<p>In other words, anything that is not explicitly <code>true</code>, is <code>false</code> in Dart. So, in our example, if <code>if (x)</code> would evaluate to
<code>true</code> if and only if <code>x</code> equalled the the boolean literal <code>true</code> (or an expression that evaluated to <code>true</code> (<code>3 % 2 == 1</code>, say)),;
otherwise it would evaluate to false.</p>

<p>This is very simple. There are no truthy/falsey lists to memorize; it is all very clear, quite correct and ....</p>

<p>likely to get you quickly into trouble. Wait, what?</p>

<p>This is legal Dart code, right? Well, that depends if you are in checked mode or not.  In unchecked mode, the code works exactly
as described above. However, in <em>checked mode</em>, any <code>if (x)</code> type constructs will generate an exception unless x is a boolean. Let's
look at that function from the language spec again:</p>

<pre><code>(bool v) {

}
</code></pre>

<p><strong>In checked mode, v <em>must be a bool</em>. If it isn't, the Dart editor will complain and throw an exception. We will never
get to the stage of figuring out whether our <code>if (x)</code> evaluates to true or false.</strong></p>

<p>Going back to other languages for a moment: I always felt that Javascript and Python had too many falsey values. I liked
that in Ruby, only <code>false</code> and <code>nil</code> evaluated to false; everything else was true. So, instead of writing <code>if myList ...</code>, you
would write <code>if myList.empty? ..</code> in Ruby, making your intent quite clear.
Dart actually goes beyond
Ruby in this regard and <em>really</em> simplifies things:  <code>false</code> (and boolean expressions that return <code>false</code>) are false;
<code>true</code> (and boolean expressions that return <code>true</code>) are true. <em><strong>Everything else is neither false nor true</strong></em>.</p>

<p>So, as a programmer, how should you handle the reality that the Dart's boolean semantics change based on whether you
are in checked or unchecked mode?  My recommendation: always code in checked mode and be quite explicit about boolean
expressions.</p>

<p>Avoid code like this (you will get an exception in checked mode):</p>

<pre><code>String s = '';
if (s) {...}
</code></pre>

<p>This can be rewritten more clearly:</p>

<pre><code>if (s.isEmpty) {...}
</code></pre>

<p>The following:</p>

<pre><code>List myList = [1, 2, 3];
if(myList.indexOf(1)) {...}
</code></pre>

<p>should become:</p>

<pre><code>if (myList.indexOf(1) != 0) {...}
</code></pre>

<p>and this:</p>

<pre><code>int num;
if (num) {...}
</code></pre>

<p>is better written as:</p>

<pre><code>if (num == null) {...}
</code></pre>

<p>The real take home lesson is a) listen to the static warnings b) only use booleans for boolean operations (Do not rely on implicit boolean
conversions) c) checked mode is there to stop you immediately if you do bad things during development. Dart works pretty hard
to force you to do boolean stuff explicitly and there are good reasons for this. Follow the warnings from the editor and your
code will be clearer, more maintainable and you will avoid a huge class of bugs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[string concatenation in dart]]></title>
    <link href="http://shailen.github.com/blog/2012/11/13/string-concatenation-in-dart/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-13T17:33:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shailen.github.com/blog/2012/11/13/string-concatenation-in-dart</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let us start with a simple helloworld.dart example and use it to see how string concatenation works in Dart.</p>

<pre><code>void main() {
  print("hello, world!");
}
</code></pre>

<p>The above works, obviously. Now, if we were given this greeting as two strings, "hello, " and "world!", and asked
to join them together, we might be tempted to do:</p>

<pre><code>"hello, " + "world!"
</code></pre>

<p>This works in lots of languages, but not in Dart. The + operator has not been overloaded in the String class, the above code throws
a <code>NoSuchMethodError</code>.</p>

<p>Not a problem: Dart gives us lots of ways to contcatenate strings. I list the most common ways
below. <em>Above the examples you will see some <strong>crude</strong> benchmarks that I calculated by running each example a million
times on my MacBook. These can give a <strong>general</strong> sense of the relative efficiency of each method</em>.</p>

<p>The easiest, most efficient way to concat strings is by using adjacent string literals:</p>

<pre><code>.041 seconds
String a = "hello, " "world!";
</code></pre>

<p>This still works if the adjacent strings are on different lines:</p>

<pre><code>.040 seconds
String b = "hello, "
    'world!';
</code></pre>

<p>Dart also has a <code>StringBuffer</code> class, and this can be used to build up a <code>StringBuffer</code> object
and convert it to a string by calling <code>toString()</code> on it:</p>

<pre><code>.689 seconds
var sb = new StringBuffer();
["hello, ", "world!"].forEach((item) {
  sb.add(item);
  });
String c = sb.toString();
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>Strings</code> class (notice the plural) gives us 2 methods, <code>join()</code> and <code>concatAll()</code> that
can also be used. <code>Strings.join()</code> takes a delimiter as a second argument:</p>

<pre><code>.408 seconds
String d = Strings.join(["hello", "world!"], ", ");

.385 seconds
String e = Strings.concatAll(["hello", "world"]);
</code></pre>

<p>All of the above work, but if you are looking for a <code>+</code> substitute, use adjacent string literals;
if you need to join a list of strings using a delimiter,
use <code>Strings.join()</code>. If you plan on building a very long string, the
<code>StringBuffer</code> class can gather the components quite efficiently and convert them to a string only
when needed.</p>

<p>You can also use string interpolation; that will be the subject of my next post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
